Chapter 38 Conclusion Reader.
I married him.
A quiet wedding we had.
He and I, the passing and clerk, were alone present.
When we got back from church, I went into the kitchen of the manor house,
where Mary was cooking the dinner and John cleaning the knives, and I said,
Mary, I have been married to Mr. Rochester this morning.
The housekeeper and her husband were both of that decent, fleagmatic order of
people, to whom one may at any time safely communicate a remarkable piece of news,
without incurring the danger of having one's ears pierced by some shrill
ejaculation, and subsequently stunned by a torrent of wordy wonderment.
Mary did look up, and she did stare at me, the ladle with which she was basting a
pair of chickens roasting at the fire, did for some three minutes hang suspended
in air, and for the same space of time, John's
knives also had rest from the polishing process.
But Mary, bending again over the roast, said only, have you miss?
Well for sure.
A short time after she pursued.
I cede you go out with the master, but I didn't know
you were gone to church to be wed, and she basted away.
John, when I turned to him, was grinning from ear to ear.
I told Mary how it would be, he said.
I knew what Mr. Edward, John was an old servant, and had known his master when he
was the cadet of the house, therefore he often gave him his Christian name.
I knew what Mr. Edward would do, and I was certain
he would not wait long neither, and he's done right.
For ought I know, I wish you joy, miss, and he politely pulled his forelock.
Thank you, John.
Mr. Rochester told me to give you and marry this.
I put into his hand a five-pound note.
Without waiting to hear more, I left the kitchen,
in passing the door of that sanctum sometime after.
I caught the words.
She'll happen to better for him nor on ear to grand ladies.
And again, if she bent one of the handsomest, she's no one foul and very
good -natured, and ah, his eun, she's fair, beautiful, only body may see that.
I wrote to Morehouse and to Cambridge immediately, to say what I had done,
fully explaining also why I had thus acted.
Diana and Mary approved the step unreservedly.
Diana announced that she would just give me time to get over the honeymoon,
and then she would come and see me.
She had better not wait till then, Jane, said
Mr. Rochester, when I read her letter to him.
If she does, she will be too late.
For our honeymoon will shine our life long.
Its beams will only fade over your grave or mine.
How singeon received the news?
I don't know.
He never answered the letter in which I communicated it.
Yet six months after he wrote to me, without, however, mentioning Mr.
Rochester's name or alluding to my marriage, his letter was then calm and,
though very serious, kind.
He has maintained a regular, though not frequent correspondence ever since.
He hopes I am happy, and trusts I am not of those who live
without God in the world, and only mind earthly things.
You have not quite forgotten little Adele, have you, reader?
I had not.
I soon asked an obtained leave of Mr. Rochester to
go and see her at the school where he had placed her.
Her frantic joy at beholding me again moved me much.
She looked pale and thin.
She said she was not happy.
I found the rules of the establishment were too strict.
It's a course of study too severe for a child of her age.
I took her home with me.
I meant to become her governess once more, but I soon found this impracticable.
My time and cares were now required by another.
My husband needed them all.
So I sought out a school, conducted on a more indulgent system, and near enough to
permit of my visiting her often, and bringing her home sometimes.
I took care she should never want for anything that could contribute to her comfort.
She soon settled in her new abode, became very
happy there, and made fair progress in her studies.
As she grew up, a sound English education corrected in a great measure her French
defects, and when she left school, I found in her a pleasing and obliging
companion, docile, good tempered, and well principled.
By her grateful attention to me and mine, she has long since well repaid any little
kindness I ever had it in my power to offer her.
My tale draws to its close.
One word respecting my experience of married life, and one brief glance at the
fortunes of those whose names have most frequently recurred in this narrative,
and I have done.
I have now been married ten years.
I know what it is to live entirely for and with what I love best on earth.
I hold myself supremely blessed.
Blessed beyond what language can express, because
I am my husband's life as fully as he is mine.
No woman was ever near to her mate than I am, evermore
absolutely bone of his bone and flesh of his flesh.
I know no weariness of my Edward society.
He knows none of mine, any more than we each do of the
pulsation of the heart that beats in our separate bosoms.
Consequently, we are ever together.
To be together is for us to be at once as free as in solitude, as gay as in company.
We talk, I believe, all day long.
To talk to each other is but a more animated and an audible thinking.
All my confidence is bestowed on him.
All his confidence is devoted to me.
We are precisely suited in character.
Perfect concord is the result.
Mr. Rochester continued blind the first two years of our union.
Perhaps it was that circumstance that drew us so very near, that knit us so very
close, for I was then his vision as I am still his right hand.
Literally, I was, what he often called me, the apple of his eye.
He saw nature, he saw books through me, and never did I weary of gazing for his
behalf, and of putting into words the effect of field, tree, town, river,
cloud, sunbeam, of the landscape before us, of the weather round us, and
impressing by sound on his ear, what light could no longer stamp on his eye.
Never did I weary of reading to him, never did I weary of conducting him where
he wished to go, of doing for him what he wished to be done.
And there was a pleasure in my services, most full, most exquisite, even though
sad, because he claimed these services without painful shame or damping humiliation.
He loved me so truly, that he knew no reluctance in profiting by my attendance.
He felt I loved him so fondly, that to yield that
attendance was to indulge my sweetest wishes.
One morning, at the end of the two years, as I was writing a letter to his
dictation, he came and bent over me and said, Jane,
have you a glittering ornament round your neck?
I had a gold watch chain, I answered yes.
And have you a pale blue dress on?
I had.
He informed me then, that for some time he had fancied the obscurity, clouding one
eye was becoming less dense, and that now he was sure of it.
He and I went up to London.
He had the advice of an eminent oculist, and he
eventually recovered the sight of that one eye.
He cannot now see very distinctly.
He cannot read or write much, but he can find his way without being led by the hand.
The sky is no longer a blank to him, the earth no longer avoid.
When his first born was put into his arms, he could see that the boy had inherited
his own eyes, as they once were, large brilliant and black.
On that occasion, he again, with a full heart,
acknowledged that God had tempered judgment with mercy.
My Edward and I then are happy, and the more so,
because those we most love are happy likewise.
Diana and Mary Rivers are both married, alternately, once every year.
They come to see us, and we go to see them.
Diana's husband is a captain in the Navy, a gallant officer and a good man.
Mary's is a clergyman, a college friend of her brothers, and
from his attainments and principles, worthy of the connection.
Both Captain Fitz James and Mr. Wharton love their wives, and are loved by them.
As to Syngin Rivers, he left England, he went to India, he entered on the path
he had marked for himself, he pursues it still.
A more resolute, indefatigable pioneer never brought amidst rocks and dangers.
Firm, faithful and devoted, full of energy
and zeal and truth, he labors for his race.
He clears their painful way to improvement.
He hues down like a giant, the prejudices of creed and cast that encumber it.
He may be stern, he may be exacting, he may be ambitious yet, but his is the
sternness of the warrior great heart, who guards
his pilgrim convoy from the onslaught of Apollion.
His is the exaction of the Apostle, who speaks but for Christ when he says,
whosoever will come after me, let him deny
himself and take up his cross and follow me.
His is the ambition of the High Master Spirit, which aims to fill a place in the
first rank of those who are redeemed from the earth, who stand without fault before
the throne of God, who share the last mighty victories
of the Lamb, who are called and chosen and faithful.
Sinjin is unmarried, he never will marry now, himself has hitherto suffice to the
toil and the toil draws near its close, his glorious sun hastens to its setting.
The last letter I received from him drew from my eyes
human tears and yet filled my heart with divine joy.
He anticipated his sure reward, his incorruptible crown.
I know that a stranger's hand will write to me next, to say that the good and
faithful servant has been called at length into the joy of his Lord.
And why weep for this?
No fear of death will darken Sinjin's last hour.
His mind will be unclouded, his heart will be undaunted, his hope will be sure,
his faith steadfast, his own words are a pledge of this.
My master, he says, has forewarned me.
Daily he announces more distinctly, surely I come quickly, and hourly I more
eagerly respond, our men, even so come Lord Jesus.
Thank you for listening.
If you like our recordings consider liking this video and subscribing to our channel,
so you don't miss any more audiobooks.